[MUSIC PLAYING]
现在，我们想想上一节课讲过的东西
感觉上它非常有趣，它有什么实际的用途吗？
我想答案肯定是“是的”
元循环求值器是非常有价值非常值得琢磨的
我曾花费一年的时间研究元循环求值器，并据此设计出不同的元循环求值器
元循环以它们自身来定义自身，因为元循环所求值的语言包含有元循环本身[此句不确定，可能大概意思是 元循环所解释的语言正是编写此元循环的语言]
这样的求值器是一种探索语言的良好媒介
如果你想添加一个新的feature，小菜一碟，只需稍做修改运行看结果就行
你可能试了一会儿，觉得不行，放弃了这个feature
你可能想试试修改一下绑定策略或者更复杂一些的东西，然后看看语言会发生什么
事实上，对于讨论与交换语言设计，元循环求值器是一个良好的媒介，它们非常容易理解，简洁简单
假如我想和在印度的Dan Friedman讨论语言设计上的想法，我只需写一个元循环求值器邮件给他
他在他的机器上运行看看效果，可能他会觉得这个设计并不好
然后他修改一番，然后再邮件给我，为什么不试试这个，会更好一些
所以我将会讲一些这方面的技术
因为，针对特定目的来设计新语言，它真的是一种必需的技术，而且还很容易
我们试着先在Lisp中添加一个非常简单的feature
在这之前，我先来谈谈feature吧
有太多的语言因为添加了过多的feature而把语言弄的混乱不堪
计算机科学家也有一个笑话说 bug总可以变成feature的事
我认为很多系统都在经受着蠕变特性的折磨
比方说George有一个很喜欢的feature，并且加入了系统
Harry也想着，我也不喜欢这个系统，然后加入了自己最喜欢的特性
Jim也这样做
要不了多长时间，系统的操作手册一定是没人能看懂的500多页的庞然大物
有时候也可能只是一个人在添加feature并且导致同样糟糕的结果
很多情况下，比如编辑器，就会有很多feature，因为你想要很多的功能并且很多功能都有些随意性
但是回到编程语言上来，我认为有太多的feature是一个灾难
还有另一种情况你之为feeping creaturism，假如这儿有一个盒子，它有一个华丽的显示器，还从中引出一个鼠标，这个盒子内部可能还有些复杂
你的编程语言可能会因为Windows内存交换，磁盘颤动等一系列问题而不能正常工作
每当你使用计算机的时候，就会唤醒鼠标进程，它会询问是否需要做什么事情然后就回去沉睡
可能你突然不小心地胳膊肘碰到了鼠标，你的计算机突然就冒起浓烟或者更糟糕的情况 [= =]
这就是由于添加feature而导致系统不能用的两种典型情况
现在我们要添加的是一个非常简单的feature
这是一个好的feature，事实上，Lisp中就有这个feature
我们都知道，像+ *这样的过程可以接受不定数目的参数
就比如 (+ (* a x x) (* b x) c)
你可以看到，+有两到三个参数，*也有两到三个参数，不管多少个参数都同样可以计算
可以接受不定数目的参数，这一点非常有用
而之前我所讲的Lisp求值器只能接受固定数目的参数，因为我用pair-up将形参与实参一一对应
假如我想定义像这样的不定参数数目的过程
我们分步来考虑
第一步，我得先有相应的语法描述，就是一种表示附加参数的表示法，而且附加参数的个数是不定的
下一步，我们之前也提到过，即，我们怎样使用新的语法得到正确的结果呢？
我们先来看一个相关的例子
我想要定义一个过程，有一个必需的参数x和剩下的一串不定数目的参数y
x是必需的，还有剩下的很多参数用y表示，y是剩下参数的列表
这个过程里，我可以这样写 (map (lambda(u) (* x u)) y)
我用一个“点号”来表明y代表了剩下的所有参数
这样，我就对问题做出了语法描述
为什么这样来写呢？因为这恰好是Lisp reader[应该是指REPL的输出]用来表示cons的一种语法
之前没有介绍过
你可能也自己尝试过，当你用cons连接两个东西，返回的结果是 ( 第一个 . 第二个)
举例来说吧，x . y 对应着这样一个序对，CAR是x CDR是y
目前为止你们所见到的过程参数都像是这样的，比如x y z，画出列表来就像是这样，x y z '()
如果我想要一个列表与之匹配的话，假设列表(1 2 3)，用来和(x y z)相匹配
用(x y z)来对应(1 2 3)
很明显的，我们先把列表的第一个元素相对应，即x对应1，然后再开始对应列表剩下的部分
假设我来匹配(x . y)，还是用(1 2 3)
我们再来看
1 2 3,我遍历过来，哦对的，x对应1，y对应剩下的列表，也就是(2 3)
所以这里选用的表示法对于Lisp来说是非常自然的
如果我就选择 x . y 来表示不定参数
还有一种可能性
我不想要一个必需的参数，或者两个或者更多，我想要所有的参数都是不必需的全部作为一个列表，这样的话所有的实际参数组成的列表就是x
举例来看，我定义一个过程，接受参数并返回参数的列表，这个匿名过程就是过程list啊
怎么来看待这一点呢？
不管怎么说，这里应该是一个形参列表，来匹配实际参数的列表
这时，这里的x就代表了所有的参数
所以这是一种特殊的语法描述，来表示参数个数完全不定的情况
一共就两种情况，上面这种和下面这种
当你构建新的语法描述的时候，一定要注意，不要与现有的语法混淆或者矛盾
引入了新的语法描述，我也总是可以分清是接收固定数目的参数，还是一定固定参数后再接不定数目的参数，更或者是参数的个数完全不确定全部由x来表示
有很多语言都是由于语法描述方面出现了混淆或者矛盾导致语言解释器的错误
比如 类ALGOL语言的嵌套if问题
现在我已经告诉你们可行的语法了，接下来要怎么做呢？
我们如何来解释它？
其实很简单
现在我来修改一下元循环
只需要修改一行
在这里
把pair-up修改一下就行
pair-up就是那个用来匹配形参与实参的过程
大部分地方都不需要修改
如果变量列表为空，而且值的列表也是空，就返回空列表
否则，就是值太多了，也即变量列表为空而值列表不是空的
如果值列表为空，但是变量列表不为空，那么就是实参给少了
如果变量是一个符号，开始有意思了，这是一种特殊情况，这是一个符号尾
情况就像这里的一样
tail部分的y是一个符号
它不是nil
也不是空列表，这里的符号尾x就是最开始的那种情况
不是另外的情况
这种情况下，我就用这个符号去匹配整个值列表
否则，我就回到以往的正常情况来一一匹配
我认为这很容易理解
就是这些
现在  答疑时间
有什么问题吗？
你说
你能再解释一下第三种形式吗？
这个？
或许你用表结构来思考它会更容易理解一些
这是一个过程，包含一个lambda
我来画出表示上面这个过程的表结构
这里是x
这些是我们的符号
过程体就是x而已
如果我来查找这个过程的形参部分，取整个结构的CADR，返回一个符号x
所以，很自然地，在pair-up中，我就用一个符号去匹配整个实参的列表
这个符号与实参的列表相绑定
上面这种情况，如果我用CADR，得到这样的结构去匹配实参列表
这里的x就匹配到整个实参的列表然后返回x这个列表，这就是这个过程所做的事
好的
大家休息一下吧
[MUSIC PLAYING]
我们接着来看
我将要介绍另一种Lisp变式，这项feature非常出名，早期的很多Lisp实现都有它
它被称为变量的动态绑定
我们现在来研究一下
我先来介绍一下是什么情况导致人们会有动态绑定这样的想法的
我不具体说是到底是什么情况，我只来举一些例子，你们说不定也会有同样的想法的
假设，我们再来考虑sum这个过程，对一串东西求和
(define sum (lambda (term a next b) (cond ((> a b) 0) (else (+ (term a) (sum term (next a) next b))))))
当我使用sum过程的时候，我可以这样来用
(define sum-powers (lambda (a b n) (sum (lambda (x) (expt x n)) a 1+ b)))
计算x^n
x从a到b取值，加1递增
我也可以写 -- 对了
乘积
product-powers
名字有点奇怪
还是不改了
有点怪，就按原来的吧
And if I want the product of a bunch of powers-- That was 12 brain cells, that double-take.
I can for example use the procedure which is like sum, which is for making products, but it's similar to that, that you've seen before.
There's a procedure of three arguments again.
Which is the product of terms that are constructed, or factors in this case, constructed from exponentiating x to the n, where I start with a, I increment, and I go to b.
Now, there's some sort of thing here that should disturb you immediately.
These look the same.
Why am I writing this code so many times?
Here I am, in the same boat I've been in before.
Wouldn't it be nice to make an abstraction here?
What's an example of a good abstraction to make?
Well, I see some codes that's identical.
Here's one, and here's another.
And so maybe I should be able to pull that out.
I should be able to say, oh yes, the sum of the powers could be written in terms of something called the nth power procedure.
Imagine somebody wanted to write a slightly different procedure that looks like this.
The sum powers to be a procedure of a, b, and n, as the result of summing up the nth power.
We're going to give a name to that idea, for starting at a, going by one, and ending at b.
And similarly, I might want to write the product powers this way, abstracting out this idea.
I might want this.
Product powers, to be a procedure of a, b, and n, which is the product of the nth power operation on a with the incrementation and b being my arguments for the analogous-thing product.
And I'd like to be able to define, I'd like to be able to define nth power-- I'll put it over here.
I'll put it at the top.
--to be, in fact, my procedure of one argument x which is the result of exponentiating x to the n.
But I have a problem.
My environment model, that is my means of interpretation for the language that we've defined so far, does not give me a meaning for this n.
Because, as you know, this n is free in this procedure.
The environment model tells us that the meaning of a free variable is determined in the environment in which this procedure is defined.
In a way I have written it, assuming these things are defined on the blackboard as is, this is defined in the global environment, where there is no end.
Therefore, n is unbound variable.
But it's perfectly clear, to most of us, that we would like it to be this n and this n.
On the other hand, it would be nice.
Certainly we've got to be careful here of keeping this to be this, and this one over here, wherever it is to be this one.
Well, the desire to make this work has led to a very famous bug.
I'll tell you about the famous bug.
Look at this slide.
This is an idea called dynamic binding.
Where, instead of the free variable being interpreted in the environment of definition of a procedure, the free variable is interpreted as having its value in the environment of the caller of the procedure.
So what you have is a system where you search up the chain of callers of a particular procedure, and, of course, in this case, since nth power is called from inside product whatever it is-- I had to write our own sum which is the analogous procedure-- and product is presumably called from product powers, as you see over here, then since product powers bind with variable n , then nth powers n would be derived through that chain.
Similarly, this n, the nth power in n in this case, would come through nth power here being called from inside sum.
You can see it being called from inside sum here.
It's called term here.
But sum was called from inside of sum powers, which bound n.
Therefore, there would be an n available for that n to get it's value from.
What we have below this white line plus over here, is what's called a dynamic binding view of the world.
If that works, that's a dynamic binding view.
Now, let's take a look, for example, at just what it takes to implement that.
That's real easy.
In fact, the very first Lisps that had any interpretations of the free variables at all, had dynamic binding interpretations for the free variables.
APL has dynamic binding interpretation for the free variables, not lexical or static binding.
So, of course, the change is in eval.
And it's really in two places.
First of all, one thing we see, is that things become a little simpler.
If I don't have to have the environment be the environment of definition for procedure, the procedure need not capture the environment at the time it's defined.
And so if we look here at this slide, we see that the clause for a lambda expression, which is the way a procedure is defined, does not make up a thing which has a type closure and a attached environment structure.
It's just the expression itself.
And we'll decompose that some other way somewhere else.
The other thing we see is the applicator must be able to get the environment of the caller.
The caller of a procedure is right here.
If the expression we're evaluating is anpplication or a combination, then we're going to call a procedure which is the value of the operator.
The environment of the caller is the environment we have right here, available now.
So all I have to do is pass that environment to the applicator, to apply.
And if we look at that here, the only change we have to make is that fellow takes that environment and uses that environment for the purpose of extending that environment when abiding the formal parameters of the procedure to the arguments that were passed, not an environment that was captured in the procedure.
The reason why the first Lisps were implemented this way, is the sort of the obvious, accidental implementation.
And, of course, as usual, people got used to it and liked it.
And there were some people said, this is the way to do it.
Unfortunately that causes some serious problems. The most important, serious problem in using dynamic binding is there's a modularity crisis that's involved it.
If two people are working together on some big system, then an important thing to want is that the names used by each one don't interfere with the names of the other.
It's important that when I invent some segment of code that no one can make my code stop working by using my names that I use internal to my code, internal to his code.
However, dynamic binding violates that particular modularity constraint in a clear way.
Consider, for example, what happens over here.
Suppose it was the case that I decided to change the word next.
Supposing somebody is writing sum, and somebody else is going to use sum.
The writer of sum has a choice of what names he may use.
Let's say, I'm that writer.
Well, by gosh, just happens I didn't want to call this next.
I called it n.
So all places where you see next, I called it n.
Whoops.
I changed nothing about the specifications of this program, but this program stops working.
Not only that, unfortunately, this one does too.
Why do these programs stop working?
Well, it's sort of clear.
Instead of chasing out the value of the n that occurs in nth power over here or over here, through the environment of definition, where this one is always linked to this one, if it was through the environment of definition, because here is the definition.
This lambda expression was executed in the environment where that n was defined.
If instead of doing that, I have to chase through the call chain, then look what horrible thing happens.
Well, this was called from inside sum as term, term a.
I'm looking for a value of n.
Instead of getting this one, I get that one.
So by changing the insides of this program, this program stops working.
So I no longer have a quantifier, as I described before.
The lambda symbol is supposed to be a quantifier.
A thing which has the property that the names that are bound by it are unimportant, that I can uniformly substitute any names for these throughout this thing, so long as they don't occur in here, the new names, and the meaning of this expression should remain unchanged.
I've just changed the meaning of the expression by changing the one of the names.
So lambda is no longer a well defined idea.
It's a very serious problem.
So for that reason, I and my buddies have given up this particular kind of abstraction, which I would like to have, in favor of a modularity principle.
But this is the kind of experiment you can do if you want to play with these interpreters.
You can try them out this way, that way, and the other way.
You see what makes a nicer language.
So that's a very important thing to be able to do.
Now, I would like to give you a feeling for I think the right thing to do is here.
How are you going to I get this kind of power in a lexical system?
And the answer is, of course, what I really want is a something that makes up for me an exponentiator for a particular n.
Given an n, it will make me an exponentiator.
Oh, but that's easy too.
In other words, I can write my program this way.
I'm going to define a thing called PGEN, which is a procedure of n which produces for me an exponentiator.
--x to the n.
Given that I have that, then I can capture the abstraction I wanted even better, because now it's encapsulated in a way where I can't be destroyed by a change of names.
I can define some powers to be a procedure again of a, b, and n which is the sum of the term function generated by using this generator, PGEN, n, with a, incrementer, and b.
And I can define the product of powers to be a procedure of a, b, and n which is the product PGEN, n, with a, increment, and b.
Now, of course, this is a very simple example where this object that I'm trying to abstract over is small.
But it could be a 100 lines of code.
And so, the purpose of this is, of course, to make it simple.
I'd give a name to it, it's just that here it's a parameterized name.
It's a name that depends upon, explicitly, the lexically apparent value of n.
So you can think of this as a long name.
And here, I've solved my problem by naming the term generation procedures within an n in them.
Are there any questions?
Oh, yes, David.
AUDIENCE: Is the only solution to the problem you raise to create another procedure?
In other words, can this only work in languages that are capable of defining objects as procedures?
PROFESSOR: Oh, I see.
My solution to making this abstraction, when I didn't want include the procedure inside the body, depends upon my ability to return a procedure or export one.
And that's right.
If I don't have that, then I just don't have this ability to make an abstraction in a way where I don't have possibilities of symbol conflicts that were unanticipated.
That's right.
I consider being able to return the procedural value and, therefore, to sort of have first class procedures, in general, as being essential to doing very good modular programming.
Now, indeed there are many other ways to skin this cat.
What you can do is take for each of the bad things that you have to worry about, you can make a special feature that covers that thing.
You can make a package system.
You can make a module system as in Ada, et cetera.
And all of those work, or they cover little regions of it.
The thing is that returning procedures as values cover all of those problems. And so it's the simplest mechanism that gives you the best modularity, gives you all of the known modularity mechanisms.
Well, I suppose it's time for the next break, thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
PROFESSOR: Well, yesterday when you learned about streams, Hal worried to you about the order of evaluation and delayed arguments to procedures.
The way we played with streams yesterday, it was the responsibility of the caller and the callee to both agree that an argument was delayed, and the callee must force the argument if it needs the answer.
So there had to be a lot of hand shaking between the designer of a procedure and user of it over delayedness.
That turns out, of course, to be a fairly bad thing, it works all right with streams. But as a general thing, what you want is an idea to have a locus, a decision, a design decision in general, to have a place where it's made, explicitly, and notated in a clear way.
And so it's not a very good idea to have to have an agreement, between the person who writes a procedure and the person who calls it, about such details as, maybe, the arguments of evaluation, the order of evaluation.
Although, that's not so bad.
I mean, we have other such agreements like, the input's a number.
But it would be nice if only one of these guys could take responsibility, completely.
Now this is not a new idea.
ALGOL 60 had two different ways of calling a procedure.
The arguments could be passed by name or by value.
And what that meant was that a name argument was delayed.
That when you passed an argument by name, that its value would only be obtained if you accessed that argument.
So what I'd like to do now is show you, first of all, a little bit about, again, we're going to make a modification to a language.
In this case, we're going to add a feature.
We're going to add the feature of, by name parameters, if you will, or delayed parameters.
Because, in fact, the default in our Lisp system is by the value of a pointer.
A pointer is copied, but the data structure it points at is not.
But I'd like to, in fact, show you is how you add name arguments as well.
Now again, why would we need such a thing?
Well supposing we wanted to invent certain kinds of what otherwise would be special forms, reserve words?
But I'd rather not take up reserve words.
I want procedures that can do things like if.
If is special, or cond, or whatever it is.
It's the same thing.
It's special in that it determines whether or not to evaluate the consequent or the alternative based on the value of the predicate part of an expression.
So taking the value of one thing determines whether or not to do something else.
Whereas all the procedures like plus, the ones that we can define right now, evaluate all of their arguments before application.
So, for example, supposing I wish to be able to define something like the reverse of if in terms of if.
Call it unless.
We've a predicate, a consequent, and an alternative.
Now what I would like to sort of be able to do is say-- oh, I'll do it in terms of cond.
Cond, if not the predicate, then take the consequent, otherwise, take the alternative.
Now, what I'd like this to mean, is supposing I do something like this.
I'd like this unless say if equals one, 0, then the answer is two, otherwise, the quotient of one and 0.
What I'd like that to mean is the result of substituting equal one, 0, and two, and the quotient of one, 0 for p, c, and a.
I'd like that to mean, and this is funny, I'd like it to transform into or mean cond not equal one, 0, then the result is two, otherwise I want it to be the quotient one and 0.
Now, you know that if I were to type this into Lisp, I'd get a two.
There's no problem with that.
However, if I were to type this into Lisp, because all the arguments are evaluated before I start, then I'm going to get an error out of this.
So that if the substitutions work at all, of course, I would get the right answer.
But here's a case where the substitutions don't work.
I don't get the wrong answer.
I get no answer.
I get an error.
Now, however, I'd like to be able to make my definition so that this kind of thing works.
What I want to do is say something special about c and a.
I want them to be delayed automatically.
I don't want them to be evaluated at the time I call.
So I'm going to make a declaration, and then I'm going to see how to implement such a declaration.
But again, I want you to say to yourself, oh, this is an interesting kluge he's adding in here.
The piles of kluges make a big complicated mess.
And is this going to foul up something else that might occur.
First of all, is it syntactically unambiguous?
Well, it will be syntactically unambiguous with what we've seen so far.
But what I'm going to do may, in fact, cause trouble.
It may be that the thing I had will conflict with type declarations I might want to add in the future for giving some system, some compiler or something, the ability to optimize given the types are known.
Or it might conflict with other types of declarations I might want to make about the formal parameters.
So I'm not making a general mechanism here where I can add declarations.
And I would like to be able to do that.
But I don't want to talk about that right now.
So here I'm going to do, I'm going to build a kluge.
So we're going to define unless of a predicate-- and I'm going to call these by name-- the consequent, and name the alternative.
Huh, huh-- I got caught in the corner.
If not p then the result is c, else-- that's what I'd like.
Where I can explicitly declare certain of the parameters to be delayed, to be computed later.
Now, this is actually a very complicated modification to an interpreter rather than a simple one.
The ones you saw before, dynamic binding or adding indefinite argument procedures, is relatively simple.
But this one changes a basic strategy.
The problem here is that our interpreter, as written, evaluates a combination by evaluating the procedure, the operator producing the procedure, and evaluating the operands producing the arguments, and then doing apply of the procedure to the arguments.
However, here, I don't want to evaluate the operands to produce the arguments until after I examined the procedure to see what the procedure's declarations look like.
So let's look at that.
Here we have a changed evaluator.
I'm starting with the simple lexical evaluator, not dynamic, but we're going to have to do something sort of similar in some ways.
Because of the fact that, if I delay a procedure-- I'm sorry-- delay an argument to a procedure, I'm going to have to attach and environment to it.
Remember how Hal implemented delay.
Hal implemented delay as being a procedure of no arguments which does some expression.
That's what delay of the expression is.
--of that expression.
This turned into something like this.
Now, however, if I evaluate a lambda expression, I have to capture the environment.
The reason why is because there are variables in there who's meaning I wish to derive from the context where this was written.
So that's why a lambda does the job.
It's the right thing.
And such that the forcing of a delayed expression was same thing as calling that with no arguments.
It's just the opposite of this.
Producing an environment of the call which is, in fact, the environment where this was defined with an extra frame in it that's empty.
I don't care about that.
Well, if we go back to this slide, since it's the case, if we look at this for a second, everything is the same as it was before except the case of applications or combinations.
And combinations are going to do two things.
One, is I have to evaluate the procedure-- forget the procedure-- by evaluating the operator.
That's what you see right here.
I have to make sure that that's current, that is not a delayed object, and evaluate that to the point where it's forced now.
And then I have to somehow apply that to the operands.
But I have to keep the environment, pass that environmental along.
So some of those operands I may have to delay.
I may have to attach that environment to those operands.
This is a rather complicated thing happening here.
Looking at that in apply.
Apply, well it has a primitive procedure thing just like before.
But the compound one is a little more interesting.
I have to evaluate the body, just as before, in an environment which is the result of binding some formal parameters to arguments in the environment.
That's true.
The environment is the one that comes from the procedure now.
It's a lexical language, statically bound.
However, one thing I have to do is strip off the declarations to get the names of the variables.
That's what this guy does, vnames.
And the other thing I have to do is process these declarations, deciding which of these operands-- that's the operands now, as opposed to the arguments-- which of these operands to evaluate, and which of them are to be encapsulated in delays of some sort.
The other thing you see here is that we got a primitive, a primitive like plus, had better get at the real operands.
So here is a place where we're going to have to force them.
And we're going to look at what evlist is going to have to do a bunch of forces.
So we have two different kinds of evlist now.
We have evlist and gevlist. Gevlist is going to wrap delays around some things and force others, evaluate others.
And this guy's going to do some forcing of things.
Just looking at this a little bit, this is a game you must play for yourself, you know.
It's not something that you're going to see all possible variations on an evaluator talking to me.
What you have to do is do this for yourself.
And after you feel this, you play this a bit, you get to see all the possible design decisions and what they might mean, and how they interact with each other.
So what languages might have in them.
And what are some of the consistent sets that make a legitimate language.
Whereas what things are complicated kluges that are just piles of junk.
So evlist of course, over here, just as I said, is a list of operands which are going to be undelayed after evaluation.
So these are going to be forced, whatever that's going to mean.
And gevlist, which is the next thing-- Thank you.
What we see here, well there's a couple of possibilities.
Either it's a normal, ordinary thing, a symbol sitting there like the predicate in the unless, and that's what we have here.
In which case, this is intended to be evaluated in applicative order.
And it's, essentially, just what we had before.
It's mapping eval down the list. In other words, I evaluate the first expression and continue gevlisting the CDR of the expression in the environment.
However, it's possible that this is a name parameter.
If it's a name parameter, I want to put a delay in which combines that expression, which I'm calling by name, with the environment that's available at this time and passing that as the parameter.
And this is part of the mapping process that you see here.
The only other interesting place in this interpreter is cond.
People tend to write this thing, and then they leave this one out.
There's a place where you have to force.
Conditionals have to know whether or not the answer is true or false.
It's like a primitive.
When you do a conditional, you have to force.
Now, I'm not going to look at any more of this in any detail.
It isn't very exciting.
And what's left is how you make delays.
Well, delays are data structures which contain an expression, an environment, and a type on them.
And it says they're a thunk.
That comes from ALGOL language, and it's claimed to be the sound of something being pushed on a stack.
I don't know.
I was not an ALGOLician or an ALGOLite or whatever, so I don't know.
But that's what was claimed.
And undelay is something which will recursively undelay thunks until the thunk becomes something which isn't a thunk.
This is the way you implement a call by name like thing in ALGOL.
And that's about all there is.
Are there any questions?
AUDIENCE: Gerry?
PROFESSOR: Yes, Vesko?
AUDIENCE: I noticed you avoided calling by name in the primitive procedures, I was wondering what cause you have on that?
You never need that?
PROFESSOR: Vesko is asking if it's ever reasonable to call a primitive procedure by name?
The answer is, yes.
There's one particular case where it's reasonable, actually two.
Construction of a data structure like cons where making an array if you have arrays with any number of elements.
It's unnecessary to evaluate those arguments.
All you need is promises to evaluate those arguments if you look at them.
If I cons together two things, then I could cons together the promises just as easily as I can cons together the things.
And it's not even when I CAR CDR them that I have to look at them.
That just gets out the promises and passes them to somebody.
That's why the lambda calculus definition, the Alonzo Church definition of CAR, CDR, and cons makes sense.
It's because no work is done in CAR, CDR, and cons, it's just shuffling data, it's just routing, if you will.
However, the things that do have to look at data are things like plus.
Because they have a look at the bits that the numbers are made out of, unless they're lambda calculus numbers which are funny.
They have to look at the bits to be able to crunch them together to do the add.
So, in fact, data constructors, data selectors, and, in fact, things that side-effect data objects don't need to do any forcing in the laziest possible interpreters.
On the other hand predicates on data structures have to.
Is this a pair?
Or is it a symbol?
Well, you better find out.
You got to look at it then.
Any other questions?
Oh, well, I suppose it's time for a break.
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]